Your source for Orthodox books, podcasts, videos, and more, we are ancient faith ministries.
He will be a staff for the righteous with which for them to stand and not to fall, and
he will be the light of the nations and the hope of those whose hearts are troubled.
who dwell on the earth will fall down and worship him.
Amable.
praise and bless and celebrate with song the Lord of spirits.
1st denoc, chapter 48 verses 4 through 5.
The modern world doesn't acknowledge,
but is nevertheless haunted by spirits, angels, demons,
and saints.
In our time, many year into break free of the prison
of a flat, secular materialism, to see and to know reality
as it truly is.
What is this spiritual reality like?
How do we engage with it well?
How do we...
permeate everyday life with spiritual presence.
Orthodox Christian priests, Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Stephen DeYoung
host this live Colin show, focused on enchantment in creation,
the union of the scene and unseen as made by God
and experienced by mankind throughout history.
Welcome to the Lord of Spirits.
I feel like one of these days we should do like a cold open,
you know, instead of...
I don't know, what do you think, Father?
Just like...
You know, I mean, it'll probably happen eventually that just we go live and don't realize
it.
We're talking about something else.
It's true.
We've had the opposite.
Yeah.
So, well, all right.
Well, good evening.
We're having the accident.
All of you, you giant killers, you dragon slayers, you warders off of the unclean.
As you are, like a word off of the unclean, is that like the guy who follows you around
bringing a bell yelling unclean
Exactly. Yes, followed by, you know, bring out your dead. Yeah, this is the Lord of
Spirits podcast. That other voice you just heard is the very Reverend Dr. Stephen D.
Young, the scourge of Semiramis. And he's with me straight from the swamp in Lafayette, Louisiana,
where they are under nine inches of snow for the first time in recorded history.
Yes. What is going on down there? Probably all frozen at it's like a cold blooded.
Bye.
That's prepared for this frozen cajun food. It's just not it's not right. Gator's not right. Yeah, yeah.
I'm father and just even Damick in the mass Pennsylvania. Where this morning it was
I think it was about three degrees and I walked outside my bearded frows
But I am currently purchased precariously atop the arcane tarp podcasting hovering dozens of stories above a disused gateway
To the underworld and we are a lot probably stop and dampening your beard before leaving the house
I know. And if you're listening to us,
slide, everybody, you can call us at a five two three seven two three four six.
You can talk to us and we're going to get to your calls in second half of the show
and our very own are very beloved.
Our very powerful.
Matt Schutte, the tank Richter, newly promoted costs newly promoted.
Yes, that's right. She's queen of all media or something over there.
Something like yes.
So I want to give a very mild parental advisory.
everybody this evening we're going to be talking about ritual
impurity in the Old Testament among other things. So that's going to include a little bit of talk about bodily functions.
Nothing explodes.
Fluids.
Fluids, yes. Nothing explicit, but it will be mentioned. So there are some who say that the ritual purification theology or the Old Testament is one of those things that gets dropped
with the coming of Christ at the churches in no way bound by either its stipulations or its ethos.
and some, seeing certain prayers or practices of the tr...
that seems to be informed by this ethos
may even decry them as aberrations
inconsistent with the New Testament.
But is this true?
Are all those Levitical commandments
about uncleanness and ritual washings
and so forth just obsolete?
Didn't Jesus just cleanse the whole world
and do away with all that?
What do you think Father Stephen?
Did Jesus just toss all that to curb?
No.
All right, good night everybody.
And while since I did that bit, so...
Yeah, I'm gonna remind you, I'll do it.
Jesus didn't toss any stuff out. Yeah, he's kind of like explicit about that actually. Yes
That one yogurt or Timmel I believe
Yoder Timmel. I don't know. I like John Tittle. That's very King Jamesy. You know, yeah
Well, so what are we supposed to do though? That stuff was like ghost ranger. What was that?
Negative ghost man. Yes childhood memories about
It's like Palabra Jot.
Wow.
For words.
For who?
I mean, yeah.
If you're growing up in LA in the late 70s, and you know, I was not about calling.
Go ahead and call during the first half if you know the answer to that.
Yeah, go ahead.
I'll be watching the lines.
Yeah.
But only for that.
Otherwise, you've got to wait till the second half.
Yeah.
I'll try and approach and horse your way in.
Yeah, so there's nothing, nothing gets dropped with the coming of cry.
nothing gets dropped in the New Tesla. We need to get past that. Right. Just get past that.
There are things that persist in basically the same form. Like, we just got a request,
which is our YouTube guy, Simon. He requested that if
If, if truly gets to be the queen of digital, something,
queen of media, he wants to be the yarl.
YouTube. What do you think, father? Should we dub him the Yarl of YouTube? Has a nice little
guy? Has he drunk meat from the skull of one of his enemies? Oh, Simon, you're going to have to let
us know. Get back on that. Because I think Yarl, that's a very important question. Yeah.
That's a basic qualification for Yarl. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. That's true.
It has to be made. Yeah. Absolutely. Otherwise, you could just be a Bulgarian or something.
So
All right, uncleanness.
Yes, but anyway, yes.
So there's some things that persist,
like the identity of God is the same in the Old Testament
and the New Testament, right?
Right.
There are other things that are transformed
by who Christ is and what he does, right?
But nothing just goes away or gets trash-bid.
Take that, Marcy Nests.
Yes.
Marcy Nests.
And lots of other crypto-Marcy Unites.
That's a lot of crypto-Marcy.
They're hiding it.
Secretly.
Who knows what evil lurks in the hearts of Marsian?
The shadow knows
Well, he knows that for everybody though
Yes, so obviously our answer to that is no, but
Obviously also this is one of those things that in certain ways gets transformed
in other ways persists in basically the same form.
More
than you might think. So that's what we're getting into tonight and part of this of course
is that in general folks don't have a good understanding of the whole clean unclean distinction
in the Old Testament in the first place. Yeah. What that's actually about what it actually
means
what it's actually distinguishing.
And the biggest problem,
and we've mentioned this at least in passing,
I know several times in the history of the show,
but the biggest thing is conflating the concept of sin
with the concept of uncleanness, person.
That somehow clean is good
Unclean is bad or even evil.
Right? These are commensurate categories. Right? And so anything that's called
unclean is some in the Old Testament, therefore is sinful. And then there's further
we're not going to go into that now, but see past episodes on the definition of bad
definitions of sin that make that a even worse mistake, right, when those get
important but so the place we have to start
in terms of actually understanding it is that there are two different kinds of
uncleanness in the in the Old Testament in the Torah really is where we're
starting. Yeah and they're not the same thing. The first is the one that is
usually the cause of conflation. That is, there is moral uncleanness.
do something evil that renders you unclean.
Unclean, you're unfit to go into the presence of God because of this evil thing that you did.
Yeah, it's not just that you're like dirty, you know, like, oh, look out dirty that person is.
It's, you can't go be with God.
You can't go into, you approach the tabernacle or the tumble and offer sacrifices.
Like you have a limitation on your behavior.
Right.
Until the problem is taking care of.
Right. Right.
Yeah.
And so that's the way people tend to think about all
uncleanness of the Torah. But that's not all uncleanness of the Torah.
Far more common is what we might call ceremonial or ritual uncleanness.
And ceremonial or ritual uncleanness is something you can track to a variety of ways
We're going to talk about here in the first half, but that is resolved.
often, if you read the Torah, it'll say the person who does this must wash and
they're unclean until evening. Or sometimes there's a longer period of like
seven days of purification and then they wash and they're clean. This is all
resolved by ritual washings of which there are a lot in the Torah and the Old
Testament and even into second-temporary Judaism. Yeah and they have, I mean,
There's references to like
like special pools in the gospels where people as they're approaching the temple, they would
wash themselves.
Yeah, and people, I think when people hear that, they don't really understand what's going
on there because I think when people hear that, they're thinking of like a Roman bath or
something like where you go in and you like, and the people are all bathing and maybe it's
like a gang shower in college.
The old people in college didn't have private showers.
I don't know how to do that.
I remember that.
that time was the worst one but
But it's not even that time of situation.
We're talking about a literal like pool of water.
And there are pools in Jerusalem
from the time of Christ that are massive.
And they have steps leading down into and then out of them.
Yeah, you just walk down in, walk through it,
and then walk up down the other side
and like dozens of people at a time.
Yeah.
It's like going it's like going
through you know passport control. Yeah. Right. You just pass through and you're good on the other side.
Now obviously there were also more private McVote and that kind of thing and there were separate men
and women's for when they're doing this in the nude, right, etc. Right. But ceremony of washing
is dealing with this kind of ritual uncleaness, right. And it wasn't that, you know, journeying
to Jerusalem was evil, but you're out there on the road.
Right? And now you're coming into the city and now you're going up to the temple to worship God and so
Right, you're clean. So this is the kind of ceremonial case that has no is not a moral category. Yeah
It's not a well. Okay. We'll see that pretty clearly as we go forward and talk a little more about it
But we have to start with this distinction
Now moral uncleanness when you do something when you actually do something sinful
you do something, what can you do something evil?
and that makes you unclean and therefore unfit to come into the presence of God
because of that evil thing you did, that includes ceremonial uncleanness, meaning
that's why in particular, you're banned from participating in worship, right?
You are ceremonially or ritually unclean because of that. But ceremonial or
ritual uncleanness does not necessarily imply moral un.
cleanness. You can be ceremonially unclean. You can be in a state where you need to watch
yourself and clean yourself before you go to worship God without having done anything evil.
But if you have done something evil, then you also need to be purified before you can go
to the presence of God and worship God. Okay, so moral uncleanness, we're going to get much more
in detail on this but we'll start by saying it's worse because it includes both.
Whereas ritual uncleanness does not include moral uncleanness.
Moral uncleanness is avoidable, at least in theory.
Right.
I say in theory because it involves just not sinning.
So it is theoretically possible not to commit any given sin.
to theoretically possible to not commit any.
I'm not saying I or anyone I know has done this recently.
Very, very unlikely.
Yeah, you're absolutely possible.
But theoretically possible.
And so, but also the, the,
there are particular sins which are
particularly associated with moral unqueenness.
Yeah.
Yeah, it's not.
He was somebody.
If you murder somebody, not just kill, but murder.
Yeah.
To some extent kill, but especially murder, right?
Right, right.
There could be mitigating circumstances, right?
Yeah, I mean, sexual immorality, which like,
that's a big list in Leviticus, 18 and 18.
Leviticus 18 has the, yeah.
Yeah, those in particular,
and idolatry of course is closely,
pagan worship is closely connected to sexual immorality.
No, historically and
Theologically, right, so that's kind of in this category too. You do these kind of things and
then you are
particularly
Morally unclean right more so than just oh, I borrowed
my neighbor's mule and
Forgot to give it back right like
That you're also technically you have sinned and until that is done
with, right? You are, you have contracted this uncleaness, but you rectify that by returning
the meal, right? Once you've committed acts, grows acts of sexual immorality, once you've
committed acts of bloodshed and violence, once you've gotten participated in pagan worship,
there's a lot more to the repentance and to rectifying that situation, right?
Okay, you can't just come.
back and say, hey, sorry about that. Yeah, oops. Yeah. I accidentally did an idolatry.
As they might be giants once said, you can't shake the devil's hand and say you're only
kidding. Yes. But I do wonder how you can stand by your racist friend. I'm just going to
that there so that people online for certificate about
of your friends or other couples I'm discussing.
Whoa, with that comment.
Wow.
I'm not saying it is someone.
I'm not even saying it is.
I'm just saying, you know how these things work.
I do on the internet.
So that's probably going to happen.
Some people are not fans of John and John.
Is that what the people are going to guess that they're going to.
So, but obviously, right, the special...
those very severe ones, those are avoidable.
Those are things you're gonna do accidentally.
Right.
You're not gonna accidentally commit gross
to exceptional morality.
You're not accidentally going to go
and participate in paying a worship.
You're not gonna accidentally murder someone.
If someone is killed by accident, that's not murder, right?
That's what the beginning circumstances.
Right.
So, right, so that's part of,
You're gonna see what would be by-
when we say avoidable, right?
A person could go their whole life
without doing at least a couple of those, right?
The ceremonial uncleaneness, though,
the kind that doesn't involve sin, right?
The kind that doesn't involve you having done some evil,
done some evil, right? But just involves you now needing to be cleaned.
You needed to wash before you could come and approach God.
That's pretty much unavoidable.
Yeah, I mean, there's there's certain kinds of ceremonial uncleaness that are theoretically
avoidable.
Like you may never touch a dead body in your whole life, although I mean people's relatives
die and they're going to be taken to bury them.
You need to bury them.
There's a commitment to bury them.
Yeah, but you theoretically might not ever be the person who does that.
Yeah.
or like yeah that I mean but
There's some that are completely inescapable like, you know,
bodily fluids being emitted from you.
Yes. Yeah.
Natural biological cycles.
Right. Women have, you know, and even, you know, emissions that men have,
like these are things that render you richly unclean.
Yeah. And so that's, that's going to happen.
You can't avoid that.
Yeah. For your whole life, you can't avoid that.
You
Yeah, and it's not about sin. It doesn't bring like moral condemnation to you by
right. You know, like no one's gonna say, oh, you buried your dead father. So now you are evil.
I mean, the opposite. Like, as you said, there's a commandment to do that. Like, you should bury the dead.
Yes. Yeah. Um, and let's be clear here. Let's be clear here because this is a very common
misinterpretation. A lot of people who come into the Orthodox Church and they read...
some of our prayers over patents, some of the forms that people use for confession talk
about, intentional and unintentional sins or voluntary and involuntary sins.
That's not what these are talking about.
Yeah, yeah.
It is not.
I have a lot of people who think, oh, well, no, a cleanness is sin and these are just the
involuntary sins.
So something could be totally involuntary to sin.
will counter argue to.
That's not what that means.
In voluntary sins, you're actually harming, you know, even if you didn't work trying to
make it happen.
Voluntary involuntary is about a tent.
Right.
Think like involuntary manslaughter.
Yeah.
Like if you hit somebody with your car and they die and you didn't work trying to hit
them with your car and you weren't even being negligent about it.
an involuntary sin. Right now. Right. But I'm talking about even legally, right? Like,
you're just setting out to drive home. You're maybe you're driving a little faster than the speed
limit, but somebody jumps out in front of your car and you hit them. That's called legally
involuntary manslaughter. Right. Exactly. Right. It's
about when we use those words in terms of sin.
Voluntary is I set out to do this thing, this wicked thing, and I did it, or I tried to
do it, or I intended to do it.
Whereas involuntary sin is, you know, I wasn't paying attention, I was thoughtless, I was
Clueless, I w-
whatever, and I did this horrible thing,
but it's not what I set out to do.
Yeah.
Right.
Why is that still considered sin?
Well, remember, sin isn't about who's guilty
and who's going to get punished.
Yeah, it's about harm that has been enacted.
Yeah, done to you and done to other people.
Right?
So if I unthinkingly say something
that deeply hurts my wife, right?
She is hurt.
It doesn't matter if I say, oh, I didn't mean that.
I wasn't thinking.
I mean, she could accept that explanation,
but that doesn't make her less hurt by what I said.
Right?
I still have to.
I can't just say, oh, I didn't mean that.
That's not what I was trying to say.
And then just walk away like nothing ever happened.
Right?
I have to.
There's more repentance needed there.
So the, the, if the effects of our actions constitutes,
then we have to repent of them.
We have to repair that damage in the same way
that if we intend to do those actions
that cause harm, we have to repent.
Right.
You know, sort of, oh, I don't have to repent.
I don't have to apologize.
I don't have to try and fix things
because I didn't mean to break it in the first place.
Like, yeah.
That dog don't want.
So
Part of this unavoidableness, the unavoidableness, though you can see if you look at how the Torah itself defines this distinction between clean and unclean.
What distinction compares it to, which is not good and bad or good and evil?
In Leviticus 10 verse 10.
Yeah, so it says yes very brief it says you are distinguished between the holy and the common and between the unclean and
clean. So you've got this parallel there, holy and common unclean clean. Right. And so the idea is
here, the holy thing is the clean thing. Right. And the unclean thing is the common thing.
Yeah. That's a very different distinction. Holy and common is a very different distinction
than good and bad or good and evil. Right. That's not remotely the same thing.
To use the example I always use.
We have a chalice for celebrating the Eucharist in our church.
At home, I have a Star Trek 2 Wrath of Con collector cup.
The chalice was not made of holy or mind from the holy mountain.
Yeah, right and blessed by a patriarch. Right. Okay. That's
not the difference. It's not a material difference between the two. One has been set apart for a particular purpose.
Yeah. It is holy, right? The chalice is only used for the Eucharist. That is it. If someone steals it from us,
right, and uses it to drink Kool-Aid at home, it's not a chalice anymore. It's not holy anymore.
Right.
The thing my Star Trek 2 rather got Clujes Cup is, it's actually rather un-com.
at this point in history, but you get my point. It's just a drinking cup, right?
A cup or a glass that you drink out of every day for whatever you're drinking, right?
So there's common and then there's something that is wholly and set apart for it's a particular
purpose, right? And so what's happening when a person has become unclean in the process of going
about their common everyday life in the camp or
in Israel or in the world or wherever, they're going to now approach God who is holy and
so they need to make themselves holy. Well, how do they do that? They sent themselves
apart. We're going to get more into detail about what that means later, but they sent themselves
apart and devote themselves now to the Lord and remove themselves for the time from those
common things. But we'll go more into detail on that. Yeah.
little bit. But so when we talk about being unclean, ceremonial unclean, not the moral
kind again, not sin, but just being unclean. We talk about that being unavoidable. Here's
a short list. Yes, and these are all from Leviticus. And well, no, no, I'm sorry. There's one
from numbers, one from Dutamant, Dutamant. Yes. But otherwise, things that can make you
unclean.
Yeah, that's like the lightning round here.
Yes.
Well, no, because some of these we need to talk about a little.
I know, I know, I know.
Yeah.
Okay.
So number one, touching something unclean.
Like you get the unclean sort of, I don't know, kudis is probably not the right word.
But if it's unclean, you become unclean by touching.
Right.
It's unclean and you touch it, right?
And this could be literally dirty.
This could be something that's come into contact with a bodily fluid.
There's gonna be something that someone who...
was unclean sat upon.
There's it right like all kinds of ways, objects,
and things that the world could become unclean.
You touch it right now, you're unclean.
Yeah.
I mean, a related example, I mean,
because like this would really fall under the first,
but you know, it still made explicit.
If you eat or drink something that has become unclean,
that makes you unclean.
As you can see.
Well here's why it's distinct.
So for example.
You get up one bright sunshiney morning and you take your earth and jar
Where you get your water right where you have your water and you go to drink some water and after you finish drinking the water
You look in there and you see that there are three dead crickets in it
Okay
Well, it's unclean right it has dead crawling things in it. So you just drank unclean water
You're now unclean right
Okay.
Uh...
Lots of other ways that can happen.
Right.
You find out the food you just ate was prepared by someone who was ceremonially unclean.
On and on and on and on.
There's something floating in your soup.
Yes.
So that's the distinction.
That's true.
You eat or drink or just touching something.
Like touching something could be touching fabric.
Right.
You could, you know, and doesn't require you to eat it.
So you pick up a loaf of bread.
break it open you see
it's moldy inside. Even if you didn't eat it, you're unclean from touching it. Yeah. Right.
So that's why those are two separate ideas. Yeah. But you can see how just that, just those two.
If those two were the only ways to become unclean, you could see how you would end up becoming
ceremonially unclean, fairly free. Yeah, probably almost every day, I mean on some level.
but
There's more but wait there's more yet. Okay, so like if you butcher even an animal that is clean like a clean animal
if you butcher clean animal and
And that's right isn't that because you're you're touching a dead body. You're touching the carcass. Yeah
Yeah, so
You you kill a lamb you kill a goat right you kill a cow which are perfectly acceptable to eat not an unclean animal
Yeah
Right clean animal, but you're the one who butchers it
right from doing all the butchering, draining the blood, getting the blood on
yourself, doing everything about your now unclean ceremonially unclean until
evening you need to wash before you go and and present yourself to the Lord.
So that's not a good that's sort of touching an unclean thing, but you started out
with a clean bit. Yeah yeah yeah and then you made it unclean by killing it. Yeah.
Yeah, we have, we have a suit.
suggestion in the YouTube chat about one way that you could end up eating an
unclean thing, Uber eats apparently.
Well, I think Bitto Honey is an unclean thing.
Absolutely repulsive.
Do those still exist even?
I think so.
Wow.
And some dark corner of the.
We, by the way, we have some mad men.
Since I'm looking at the YouTube chat here,
actually, we have a decently international audience
once again.
We do have people from places like Hawaii and Texas.
And we realize Hawaii and Texas are part of the United States.
So I know, I know.
I was going to say but also, Norway, Brazil, Bavaria.
Yeah.
And other Americans like Florida, some neighbors actually
Walnut Port, Pennsylvania, which is about 35 minutes.
from me or so. Is that a port where they brought in Walnuts or is it a port that just
I don't know why it's called that it's like it's not it's not I'm trying to remember does a
Lehigh River actually run through there. It was founded by some dude his last name was Walnut.
That's probably what it is. One comment one commenter says parents of toddlers must have just never
been cleaned. I mean that seems like he'd be doing the mikva every day. Yeah I think toddlers
cells are innately unclean. Yeah. It's tossed the kids in the
mikbo before they go to bed. Yeah. Oh, someone from the Netherlands.
Yeah. Yeah. Portland, Oregon. See, I don't know that that's
actually America. Oh, it is. It's just America in the 90s. Oh,
that's true. Dream of the 90s is alive and alive in Portland.
Yeah. Yeah. Okay. All right. Some more things that make you
giving giving earth
Giving birth makes you unclean. Yes, which is not a bad thing. No. I mean again, these are not sinful acts
That's so important that these are not simple acts, right?
Obviously, if I say it makes you unclean giving birth this is by saying this makes you unclean
They are not saying there's something sinful about giving birth. Yeah, right, right?
Very obviously giving birth is a good thing right not an unbelievable. Obviously if you've been there
there. Right, it's seen one.
happened, right? A baby being delivered. You need to clean up. Yes. I have seen this with
my own eyes four times. Yes. I was bigger than how to take pictures of the baby like right
then with like the goo all over them. You know my fourth child. And then you could show it
to future suitors, right? They hope to date your daughter. Might be like, have you seen her baby picture?
Yeah, my, no, my daughter, we will be accepting in review.
together stacks of applications. But my fourth child was born inside his, his sack, what they would
use to call a call birth CAUL, which I'm told is like one in 80,000 births, I get crazy. And
you know, there's all kinds of medieval legends and stuff about that sort of thing. Being being
important with that but by the way I want to clarify a misconception
If anyone heard what you just said and think that you're just super protective of your daughter, it's not that.
It's you wanted to go and shake the bride price.
Okay, no, those does.
You're offering me how many goats?
This is an insult, sir.
You know, the guy that was just here before you offered this, you know,
it's got a little bidding going on.
I'm not a young ram, a kid.
No.
I mean, I'm sure she will walk away a very rich woman.
Yeah.
Yes, giving birth.
Also, various skin conditions.
I mean, this is what's behind the gospel of the 10 lepers, right?
Yes, yeah.
But also, you have to remember leprosy, the Old Testament, is not always Hanson's disease.
Yeah, it could be a lot of different things.
It's just sort of like a word that means skin disease.
It seems, right?
Like, and hence, the disease is not...
having Bob stuck in your head also by the way.
It's actual horrible.
I feel like that we should use that term for that also.
I mean, it is spelled differently, but yeah.
So I guess it's open and printed.
You know, I think one of those young men
is now in Orthodox Deacon.
Yeah, it said his G is.
I know.
I do not know the name, the names of the Hansons.
Yeah.
And having been an already adult male at the time of the time of their
embuffing scene. Yes.
I think this is the first time the Hances have been mentioned on this show.
Pretty sure on here on episode 108.
I don't even think I mentioned Stan Hansen on here.
So yeah, the very skinking is just milking in your house.
Yep, yep, right. Better start cleaning that shower more off.
just say CLR. I'm going in there. And now here's the parental advisory. Semidal emissions.
Right. Which, yeah, which I mean, it doesn't matter how you got there. It still renders you. Yeah.
Richell, there are different times. Yeah. Yeah. If it's in the context of sexual relations with one's wife,
You're just done.
until sundown. Right? In the Torah. If it's outside of that context, or if it is any kind of
discharge other than a seminal discharge from the same anatomy, then you're unclean for a week.
You go, guys. Just object to fine in the state of Mississippi. The
Yeah, if you miss...
And this is deliberately paralleled with, by deliberately paralleled, I mean it's in the same chapter of Leviticus, Leviticus chapter 15.
And they're back to back and the language is directly parallel to make this point.
That is directly paralleled with menstruation.
Right, which I mean it's funny there are some people who are super concerned about
enforcing
of these things with regards to women and you're not seen to have realized that it is exactly parallel
to for men. Yes, in both. Yes, and directly and deliberately so. Yeah, right. And the idea in both
cases is that procreation didn't happen. That's not evil. That's not a sin, right. But it is, it does
Let us render one unclean.
Right. Getting pregnant does not render you unclean. Being pregnant does not make you
unclean. Eating roadkill. That news fellow southerners. I was gonna say also Alaskans.
You know they a lot of Alaskans are on a big waiting list to get a moose. That must be
There's a lot of deer hunters in the Midwest who are using a Chevy not a rifle.
I mean, it is said that they won't let you graduate from St. T. Con's seminary if you don't kill at least one thing with your car.
Well, I did not. Well, I was at St. T. Con's seminary.
But I also just as far as you've never even agreed from there.
There you are.
No, there are a couple of times when I slowly on that hill leading to Carbondale, I rolled up slowly on a deer standing in the road.
But I'm avoided.
I think I caught a squirrel or two. I'm not sure to be honest.
Did you eat her?
I did not eat them.
Okay, good.
Because you would have been unclean.
That's in Leviticus, too.
When we get out of Leviticus at Numbers 19,
burying the dead makes you unclean.
And this is literally a good thing to do.
This is literally something you're committed to do.
A commandment from God.
And finding someone who is dead,
who you're not related to and giving them a proper burial
is considered a great good deed.
But it also makes you unclear.
Because you're handling a human corpse.
Right? Don't tell me you're gonna handle a human corpse and not wash your hands.
Right?
And then finally, just in case you thought you could avoid all of those.
uh uh
Deuteronomy 23 13 14
Deficated. Yeah, you got some more bodily functions
makes you unclean. And there were groups in the first century, including apparently some of the
people at Comron, though not all of them, who were so serious about not doing anything unclean on the
Sabbath that they would not defecate on the Sabbath. Wow, that's dedication. In a weird way, yes.
But even they knew that it was just unclean and not evil.
It's not a sin to go to the bathroom.
Right?
It's going to the bathroom.
But employees must wash their hands before returning to work.
You have to wash yourself.
You have to clean yourself after that.
It's another Toshiba Day commercial here.
But you clean yourself after you defecate, right?
Because you're unclean if you don't.
And let's look at these, right?
Collectively, not just the last one.
But what we're talking about here is these things that happen
that you can't avoid, right?
But for this to enter into the realm of sin, right, this can become a sin issue.
If you attempt to approach God for worship, after doing one of these things, without cleansing,
without washing, without purifying yourself.
So yes, somebody who defecates, it doesn't clean themselves and then wants to go into the
tabernacle. Yeah.
Right or a woman who menstruates and doesn't clean herself
And wants to go to the to the tabernacle or
So what are the skin condition right what on and on and on right the refusal?
To clean yourself properly afterwards and
The approach to God then it becomes this issue because you've brought uncleanness
into the presence of...
a holy God, right? You failed to consecrate yourself. You failed to set yourself apart before worship.
Right? This is the idea of entering into worship, entering into the presence of God in this way that is casual and common and
unserious. See Nehda Bina Bahu and other biblical examples. Right? That's where it becomes a sin issue. But in and of itself, assuming you then take the next step,
you
of cleaning yourself and preparing yourself before you come back to worship God after doing
these common things, common everyday things, there's no sin issue here.
Now someone, you know who you are, you know exactly who you are, is hearing this and saying,
Um, actually, I looked up some of those things in the Torah you mentioned.
And they say when you re-enter the life of the community,
you re-enter the religious life.
When you come back to the tabernacular to the temple,
you have to offer a sin offering.
So, ha, techmate, father Steven D. Young, yes.
Ha, clearly.
Those things are sinful in some way, right?
But here's what we're not thinking about
when we make that argument.
Right
Here's what we're not thinking about.
We're not thinking about the fact that
if you've been unclean for some period of time,
right, you've been the state of uncleanness
for some period of time.
That means by virtue of being unclean,
you've been separated at least partially
from the life of the community,
from the worship of God.
For a long time or a short time,
but there's been some period of time.
Guess what you've done during that period of time?
Sit. Yeah. Right.
And since you've been cut off from that community and religious life,
you haven't been able to engage in the kind of repentance and in the regular
cycle of offerings during that time in which you were unclean because you were
excluded from that by being unclean.
So now that you're being restored, right, the sit offering is about...
those sins and that repentance that couldn't take place for the last however long,
seven days, ten days, forty days, that you were separated from the community in
its life. Yeah, because you're gonna sin every day. Yeah, and those are not
only separations, right? We also have to think about you know people going on
long journeys. Yeah, we need to think about people going to war.
And everything they come back with, right, after that long separation, right?
When you have these extended periods away, there is this process, a part of that process
is at the time that you are away dealing with the things you've done, not all of which
were great.
Right?
And so that's why the sit-off room gets incorporated.
But ultimately as we said, and this gets to make clear and Leviticus chapter.
The only place sin enters is with the person who refuses, who wants to remain in an unclean state and yet approach God in that state.
Yes, so in Leviticus 7 verses 19 through 21, we read this,
flesh that touches any unclean thing shall not be eaten. It shall be burned up with fire.
All who are clean may eat flesh, but the person who eats the flesh of the sacrifice of the Lord's peace offerings,
while an uncleanness is
on him, that person shall be cut off from his people. And if anyone touches an unclean thing,
whether human uncleanness or an unclean beast or any unclean to testable creature,
and then eats some flesh from the sacrifice of the Lord's peace offerings,
that person shall be cut off from his people. So it's almost like saying,
if you're in an excommunicated state and you go and commune, like this will be the kind of the
analog of
Yeah, in the church.
Then you're anathema, like thrown out.
Yes. There's a process of restoration.
Yeah. There's an appropriate process of approaching God.
And remember what the whole Torah is aimed at, making that approach safe for sinful people.
Right.
And you can't sort of circumvent or end run or ignore that process and the reality.
Because it's not just like a bunch of arbitrary rules.
Yeah, yeah, the things, when God says this makes you unclean,
or especially this makes you morally unclean,
he's describing reality as it actually is.
He's not saying, okay, I've made a bunch of rules,
and I'm gonna zap you guys if you don't follow them.
If you do this thing, then you are unclean,
And you need to be cleaned up before you can do, you know,
come be with me and eat the sacrifices in my presence.
So, all right, well, that is the first half
of this episode on ritual purity
in on the Lord of Spirit's podcast.
We're gonna take our first break
and we'll be right back.
Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Stephen DeYoung
will be back in a moment to take your calls
on the next part of the Lord of Spirits.
Give them a call at 855-237-2346.
That's 855 AF Radio.
During one of the darkest times in recent history,
God gave us a saint. This saint had to be someone stubborn, stubborn enough to outshine evil
even when confronted with it face to face. But how did saint Maria become a person
whom God could inspire, help, and guide during such a dark time? How did she wrestle with her own
temptation.
and allow Christ to grow brightly in her soul.
Stubborn love by Rita Thola is one book in three parts,
written for young people.
Her life tells the story of Mother Maria Scopstova
of Paris from birth to death.
The first section of the book is accompanied
by graphic novel style illustrations
to help the young reader imagine her work, family,
and adventures.
Her writings comes next, a smattering of some of the notes
and thoughts that she...
your life is the final section where the reader is challenged to consider his or her place in the world
using Mother Maria's life and sayings as a springboard for journal entries and also some group study questions to answer
Pray for us dear Mother Maria
You can find this book at store.angentfaith.com
Again, that is store.angentfaith.com
We're back now with the Lord of Spirits, the Father-
Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Stephen DeYoung.
If you have a question, call now at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF radio.
Welcome back everybody.
Second half of this episode on purity,
ritual purity, ritual and purity,
cleanness, uncleanness on the Laura Spirits podcast.
We need to pause briefly so I can attack our audience.
Oh, go for it.
Yeah.
Yeah, so like, look you guys, nobody called in, right?
I'm like, what is this half-remembered
collaborative job thing?
Right?
No one called it.
During that commercial, super short AFR commercial,
by the way, what's it get?
I Googled it, right?
It's a show called The Right Channel 1978 PBS show.
Like, this is totally easy.
I asked you people to call in and help me.
I'm here for it nightly pouring out my heart and soul to you.
And you can't even do a Google form.
Really?
Really.
Someone asks if spam is unclean.
Which I think it must be because isn't it at least theoretically mostly pork?
I'm not sure.
I'm not really sure either.
It is the spam goo across the top of separate thing than the spam.
It could be the spam itself is clean but the goo is unclean.
I live done Guam.
I mean, spam honestly was a very common element
in the island's diet.
It's a big deal on Hawaii, too, apparently.
They love the spam.
I have heard that that is true.
Yeah.
I know.
I know from a lack of abundance of options.
Yeah.
I mean, it's canned meat.
Have we ever had a listener from Guam?
If you are on Guam right now, and listening, please.
I want to hear from Qua Manian.
They don't care about us.
We're just here.
We're dancing monkeys here for their amusement.
Not gonna lift up finger.
I'm not so much angry as I am disappointed at all.
Anyway, yeah, yeah.
All right.
Where were we?
We're beginning the second half of the program.
That's right.
second half of the program.
Which actually isn't about
spam. I know. No, not as such. I mean, spam is kind of an
athema, but yeah, that's not even really true. I got to be
honest here. I fried spam now and then as a kid, I didn't
mind it. Yeah, fried on a sandwich. It was fine. Yeah.
Fine. I've had no, I mean, I haven't had it in a long,
long time. But when I was a kid, living, you know, 13
degrees north.
I don't remember anything bad about it.
It's not as good as steak.
You remember steak-ups?
Oh, man.
Although I have to say living in the Lehigh Valley of Pennsylvania, Scrapple is an amazing
thing.
Well, see now you're going to be like actual food.
I'm talking about consumer mass market meat products.
Right.
Oh, man.
Scrapple's actual food food.
Right.
Like, yeah, it's all that's left over after you've taken out the meat and the meat and
It's pretty much everything else. Plus, I don't know, oatmeal or something.
Yeah, it's just about the topic of childhood food and I'm airing grievances.
And my mother might actually be listening to this episode. You know, it was nasty.
I don't know if your parents got in on this trend in the early 80s, this health food trend, but carob.
He said, carob instead of.
Oh, I remember that. It was never, never as good as actual top.
It was vile.
Never. Yeah. Yeah.
Yeah, it was well, I add to the fact
that you think you're getting chocolate.
And so there's the whole epic disappointment.
Yes, right.
I know.
Good riddance.
Yeah, don't eat healthy kids, it's not worth it.
Anyway.
See, that's gonna go into the clip, you know?
Back to our show.
Yeah.
Oh, okay.
Seriously, they're gonna be like,
you can eat all this healthy food,
you'll live to be 99.
I'm like, yeah, 99 miserable years.
Okay. So, yeah, so now we need to zoom in a little bit.
Okay, right, because we distinguished in our first half between sort of ceremonial or ritual
and cleanness on the one hand.
And on the other hand, moral uncleanness.
Oh, we do have a collar actually.
Oh, okay, let's hear that.
Yeah, yeah, I mean, this is super relevant.
So we have a caller from, well, at least this person's phone
is from Alabama.
You never know these days where people's phones are from,
whether that's where they're really from.
So Georgia, are you there?
I am.
I'm about to.
Is this Georgia break?
Wait, no, wrong podcast.
See, Georgia was an actual, everybody,
Georgia, it was a different podcast.
You tell them.
uh
was a gift on another pie exactly. Thank you.
A big Michael Scott slamming in the table. Thank you. Anyway, sorry, sorry, you could tell
I'm still a little traumatized by people have people downplay my portfolio. So it's on your mind,
or just. Hi, father. Um, I saw this kind of question for a long time. Um, kind of multiple questions,
but about the impurity of the
which will impurity of a woman after she's given birth.
And sort of with what's going on when she comes back
to the church and there's a special prayer said.
And some of the language in that prayer
sounds to an outsider or to a first time
are kind of more like they're dealing with a sin impurity
than a ritual impurity.
And I don't know if that's a translation issue.
And part of my question also kind of
I realized we...
But recently that how I've been interpreting, you know, the him to the San
of Tocos without corruption, that gave his first to God the word, I've been
misinterpreting that for about 10 years now as a synopurity thing when I've asked
to preach recently and he was saying, well, no, this has to do with her, you know,
her physical state and giving birth without physical harm. So could you talk
about where and what's going on. You know why why's there?
Why is there this prayer for women when they come back and how can we better understand,
you know, what that prayer to the priest says is doing for that woman and making her
ready to re-enter the church?
Yeah.
I mean, in a lot of ways, I think this is ground zero for a lot of the misunderstandings
about ritual impurity as it continues to exist in the Orthodox tradition.
Like, there are people, I mean, I said this at the beginning, but like there are people
we say, oh we don't-
don't do that anymore.
And if you have prayers that include that,
that needs to be revised or whatever.
And the truth is, of course, that Eucologian prayers, which
is the kind of thing that you're talking about.
I mean, the Eucologian includes lots.
Like, it's like all the kinds of prayers
that a priest might say outside of the context
of regular church services, typically.
So the Eucologian includes this kind of thing
and includes house blessings, et cetera, et cetera.
But so there I mean, there are.
various prayers that have been used at different times and places for this purpose.
But a decent number of them do indeed include language of ritual impurity, cleansing from
uncleaneness, and forgiveness of sins.
I mean, that's all there.
And there are people that are like, oh, no, you can't say that.
And I think it's precisely because people are conflating ritual uncleaneness.
with moral uncleanness.
You know,
as we said in the first half, right?
Like moral uncleanness includes ritual uncleanness,
but ritual uncleanness does not necessarily include
moral uncleanness.
Like we said, you can become
ritually unclean by burying your dad,
which you're supposed to be doing.
So, I mean, I think that
You know, what?
What do the prayers actually do for the woman?
Actually, there's two sets of prayers going on there in a church.
This is one of those places where different Orthodox traditions do this a little bit differently.
There's the prayers said for the woman when she comes back and then there are the prayers
that are said to church the baby, generally speaking in the Russian tradition, the churching
of the baby happens only after the baby's been baptized.
whereas in Greek and Antiochian, and I'm not sure.
which outs traditions, those prayers happen are explicitly done before baptism.
Yeah. So, I mean, what do the prayers do? I mean, they do what they say they do,
right? Like literally. But I mean, the summary I would give.
That's not the 10. Yeah, exactly. That's what it says on the 10.
But to summarize it, though, I would say, like, okay, so a woman when she gives birth,
She's the tradition that she's
days home for 40 days. And it really is about staying home. Not I've known of some people
it's like, well, I can go everywhere but church. I'm like, ah, I mean, if anyone has had
a baby, they know how nice it is to stay home. Right. Yeah. I mean, I always told people
and this is just, this is a pastoral call, but it's the tradition that I was given. I always,
I always told women that asked me about this kind of thing because I'm not going around
tell him now this is what you must do.
I would say, look, if you're out and about,
you know, and especially if you're taking the baby places,
like other than like medical appointments, okay?
If you're taking the baby places or whatever,
then you should just go ahead and come to church
and we'll do the prayers, you know, even if it hasn't been 40 days.
I mean, the ideal is to stay home the whole time
and really, you know, have that time.
Interesting.
But what it does is it's
So she's been, she's not been receiving communion for six weeks, you know?
So she's not currently in communion.
She's not excommunicated exactly, but she's been out of communion for, you know, more than
the three Sundays that puts you out.
So but she hasn't committed a sin, you know, by, you know, by being away in this context,
but you still want a prayer to be said.
So it's not like, oh you have to come to confess.
because you had a baby. No, it's not that. It's okay. You've been out of communion, so let's bring you back into communion.
And so therefore it is about this cleansing from ritual uncleaness.
You know?
Okay.
And for the baby, it's actually about welcome to church.
You know, in the Greek and Antiochian traditions, welcome to church.
We're going to be baptizing you soon. That's basically a lot of what's going on. And we're offering you to God.
You know?
in the Russian tradition, it's, you know, you've just been baptized, and so we're offering you to God.
That's my best understanding of that anyway.
I mean, I certainly have thoughts.
I, with regards to, you know,
Adia Thoro, right, which is without corruption,
there's some translations that says without to file, I'm like,
stop it. She's not, you know, like women, other women are not defiled.
but
bye
I'm going to be.
Yeah, that was what was giving me a lot of difficulty
for a long time with that particular hint.
And I mean, I know I'm going on and on
and Father Stevens being very patient,
but you know, he gets the monologue a lot in the show.
So I'm looking up old PBS shows from the late 70s.
Oh great, enjoy.
So happy night.
So there's also, and now I'm about to just tell you
what is my understanding, what I was told actually.
So like, you'll often hear an anti-occurge in the US.
More and more you hear without corruption, but in previous years you would hear without stain.
Without stain.
And my, at least what I was told by an Arabic speaker, which I am not an Arabic speaker.
I know some Arabic but not much.
I was told by an Arabic speaker, well, the translation in Arabic used to say effectively without corruption.
but the Arabic word for corruption that was being used eventually became like a bad word.
like it's not a people would snicker, you know, when they heard it in church because it was like a bad work.
It had become, and so they switched it to another word in Arabic, which gets translated then into English as steam.
You know, yeah, yeah, but it's like, we'll look in English, you know, none of these words are bad words.
So let's use corruption.
Although, of course, of course, people, people often misunderstand corruption as moral corruption.
Like we...
say, oh, that person's corrupt. But literally what corrupt means is is broken apart.
You know, without damage. Yeah, exactly. And that's what we talk about, you know,
relics being in corrupt. If they're, that doesn't mean that human bodies are, you know,
that human bodies that decay are equal, right? They are corrupt. They're literally corrupt. But
but that means they're breaking down is what's happening.
And so the tradition is.
that her birthgiving didn't include that.
Miraculous.
Wow.
You know?
So it doesn't mean that she did it without doing or, you know, having evil because that suggests
that every other woman that it's evil.
It's super not, you know, but with every other woman, it is corrupt in that sense of breaking
up.
I mean that's just a physical reaction.
Right. So yes.
Father Steven, I don't know, did you find anything in those old PBS shows or?
Yeah. Well, yeah.
I'm debating how angry I want to make certain russophiles.
But yeah.
It's pretty obvious they changed their practice historically.
Yeah. Anybody who studied it, they changed their practice from the Byzantine practice.
and it's pretty clear they did.
because it's a misunderstandings.
But yeah, and yeah, not enough, I think, is, I don't think people realize enough.
So this is part of, this is going more directly to your question, even though it's not starting
out there.
But again, you know, people don't read the Torah enough.
Amen.
And so, you know, for example, they don't notice the fact that, hey, you know what, in
In the Torah it was just first born males who were brought.
No.
Now it's everyone.
Yeah, right. It's everybody now.
Yeah. People don't even think about that.
Like why that is?
Because everyone in the church now has first born status.
They're now a co-air with Christ.
They're a co-inheritor.
So women are first born sons in the church.
There's no like second class, right?
Like Christian in the church.
That's why the ancient church used to bring female...
if it's into the altar.
Yep, people freaking out all over the place.
Did they really?
Oh, absolutely.
They really?
Absolutely.
And that practice has been restored
in significant parts of the Orthodox world.
I am sure that Father Thomas Hocker would do that.
I don't know if that's true or not,
but I was curious about that.
Yeah, because the action is about an offering.
Well, the action is not about, like, and it's
if it's haven't sinned yet.
Right, right, exactly.
and
I mean, this is a place where we're going to go get added, but we might as well just go full throttle here, but
There's this idea like I've heard people say oh well boys should be brought
Into the altar during this ritual and not girls because someday they might
Get ordained I'm like excuse me most of them are not good here
The that's why they're altar boys though, so if you don't want your son to get ordained you shouldn't be an altar boy
That's right. It's not.
three babysitting you guys.
I thought they could look cute in their little robe.
No, no, you know.
So it has nothing to do with that,
because if you look at the actual prayers of churching,
of an infant, they don't say anything about ordination
or anything like that.
Like it's not.
It's about offering this child to God.
Right, because it's related to
what we're gonna celebrate on February 2nd.
Exactly.
Exactly. The dedication of the first born, right? And out of the earth, first respect. But likewise, right? Likewise.
Not a lot of people are conversant in Leviticus chapter 12,
which is where we get exactly the procedure we follow. Yeah.
That a woman is considered to be unceremonially unclean for 40 days after giving birth.
which is this time of purification, restoration, healing,
at which point she goes and presents herself
and returns to the full regular life of the community.
And at that point, just like anyone who's been away
from the church for more than a month, right?
Anyone who's been away for that time.
There's a sit-off right.
Right?
Nazarites, well they took a Nazarite vow,
which was that they were gonna live
this higher standard of holey.
for some period of time.
At the conclusion of living in a higher standard of holiness
than everyone else, they offer to sin offering.
How about that?
Because they were now no longer going to be set apart,
they were gonna be reintegrating back into the community.
They've been away from the community.
So those prayers are just related to,
that's it, you don't have to bring two birds with you.
I don't have to ring their nacks and...
I think the blood all over the place, right?
Which is nice.
Yes.
Right?
It's nice.
A lot more sanitary.
But I kind of like little birds.
Maybe I can offer for us appreciate it when we don't do that.
Yeah.
Right?
Well, yeah, it would get splattered all over you too.
So you know.
All right.
Well, yeah.
A lot more fits.
Right.
So that's what.
And then again, people don't understand.
And this is a general problem.
So again, all you folks out there who think I'm always
straw manning and being mean and mocking
Protestants and Roman Catholics, here's another place
are going to be self-critical.
A lot of Orthodox folks, even Orthodox scholars,
are people who present themselves as such.
And this are that field.
When they see something like this,
liturgically or in our tradition, they respond by
just saying, oh well, that's not right. That doesn't fit with our Orthodox theology. So they go digging
in the crates to find some ancient Bulgarian version of the prayer that they can translate in a way
that sounds better to them or something. They don't explore why. They don't say, oh that's weird.
Why do we do that? And if they did more of, hey, that's odd. Why do we do that? Then instead of
trying to change.
these things, they would learn from these things. Yeah. Which is what we should all be doing.
We should be learning from our tradition, not trying to make it conform to some idea we have in
our head of what pure orthodoxy is. Yeah. Well, Georgia, you got a big long set of rants from the two
two of us. Yeah, no. This episode is one long fest of us.
Well, thanks for-
Well, thank you, Father.
That's very helpful.
Thanks for calling.
Nice to speak with you again.
Thank you.
All right.
Everybody, go out and buy George's book.
It's called Icon.
Yeah, she's got a couple of books, actually.
But- Oh, she wrote that book?
Yeah.
She's great.
Yeah, I should know who people are probably.
Yeah.
Go buy her book, everybody.
All right.
First, I'd have to answer that greatest of all questions.
Who am I? Who are you? Who are we? Can we go over all that again? And you and you are me and we are we and we are all together. Indeed. Indeed.
Yeah. So we got we have another call actually. We have we have father a manual calling from Reading, Pennsylvania. So to tell us we're wrong.
Father of Man you well. Welcome to Laura's pierce.
I'm on his. Thank you.
So my question has to do with everything you talked about and the first half and you were
just talking about just now how does all this correlate and maybe you're going to get to
this with who's allowed in the altar because many people, some people may be will say that
women can't go in the altar kind of at the blanket statement because of menstruation and
related things but I mean there's that kind of worms of women's ordination and all that
So
but women's monasteries, nuns, et cetera.
So why not?
Other women in other contexts and then about the purification
in that you were talking about in the first half,
how does this hold for male clergy,
major in minor clergy and even lay altar servers,
which I understand are not really supposed
to be a thing in our tradition.
But what are the times when?
We have to purify ourselves and how, aside from the ritual hand washing that the company
is the investing prayers.
Yeah.
Great question.
I mean, some of this, yeah, you're obviously tracking with us, right?
Like there is the hand washing.
But and also, of course, you know, I mean, just a little bit of spoiler for something
a little later the episode, but like you're supposed to clergy, you're supposed to abstain
from marital relations.
night before the Bible Liturgy is to be celebrated.
So yeah, and the commandments of St. Basil the Great
to priest which are in the front of a lot of different
editions of liturgy gone and talk about being at peace
with everyone, there's all kinds of stuff like this
that are these kinds of acts of purification.
I'll kick it over to the Father Stephen
for a lot of the rest of this, but I do wanna mention,
right?
Like a lot of these debates about women going behind the altar.
It has nothing.
to do with women's ordination. That's the problem is it's been completed with that question
because like there was a point when the Empress would go into the altar area to commune and no one
was asking whether or not she should be ordained. Like nothing to do with ordination at all.
You know, so Father Steve. I'm just storyus wanted to throw her out. That's what started the whole
change. Right. It's an arctic an arctic. Yes. The one to throw her out.
Yeah.
Although I do with the story is especially I do kind of get the vibe sometimes that he bumble did do it
Hmm
Like he just started making arguments. I got back to do a corner and decided to sort of like a Calvinist just double down
Bite down really hard. Yeah, just no, that is what I'm saying. Yeah
Which is saying yeah, yeah, it's just call everybody's bluff
But
Yeah, the rule with the altar is no one is allowed
behind the iconostasis, right?
Unless they're there for a particular purpose
that they've been blessed to do so by the bishop.
That's the rule.
Yeah, right.
So I don't go and hang out back there.
And I tell my parishers, I don't go hang out back there.
I don't sit back there and read.
Like while I'm waiting for people to show up, right?
and you shouldn't do that, right?
And so no one has like a right to go back there
based on their biological sex or something, right?
People who think they have a right to serve in that,
you know, at alter or to be ordained need to read about
Kora again, in the book of Numbers,
it doesn't go so well for him.
What do you make of that argument?
Yeah.
But
And so yeah, in a women's monastery, there are women who are blessed to go back there and do certain things
By the vision. So that's fine. No one else should be back there. Part of the problem too
I
Guess itself critical night is a lot of a lot of actual parishes. I've been in our far too casual about the
I've even been guilty of this and I've been trying to crack down on it
far too casual about.
the sanctuary. There's a people coming back there to ask questions during the
service or slip somebody a note or you know what I mean like people coming in
and out. People talk having conversations back there that don't need to be
had there. Yeah. That could be had over in the bestry or outside the iconostasis.
You know we were a little casual about it and the more kind of casual we are
about it, the less.
clear it is to everyone there that this is a holy place and this going back is
I mean, what we've been saying on this show says we get potentially dangerous
Right spiritually.
And something that should be undertaken with with with due reverence.
Father Andrew had sort of the preparation aspect
for clergy and the
including. I mean, Toshi isn't actually paying us to advertise their product. I'll take
their money. Wow. But yeah, I mean, even I'm thinking that like the anti-okinarched
agencies at least our priest guide, one of the first things it says is that the priest
showing up to serve a service to present himself clean.
I did, you know, vestibits clean and good repair, right?
I mean, that stuff is literally there, right?
And so, you know, that's not something that,
I think it's actually clearer in the case of clergy
that it sometimes is across the board.
How this clean, uncleaned distinction has been kept.
Because of course, just like in the Old Testament,
clergy are called to hire.
level of holiness. You wouldn't know it to look at me, but clergy at general
cards a higher level of holiness than the average layperson. And so that makes
it a little more clear. We have more things to point to that is obvious to a
layperson. Yeah. So you mentioned a bit ago about
about, um, alter servers being like, uh, pre-
training ground. I mean, is that the only reason that we have male altars servers and not female altars servers?
Pretty mild showing. Yeah, I mean, it's not like it, I did have seminaries for most of the
churches. Yeah, I was a sex. How you learned the services. I don't I don't recall like I do know that
for instance, the prayers, at least in the Russian tradition for making a reader, actually include the
line, you know, reader is the first degree of the priesthood, you know, and with references
to the possibility of...
of reaching a higher degree or whatever. But I mean, that's the thing about a lot of these
kinds of practices of the church is that we just have the rubrics for doing the thing.
There's no like marginalia saying, and this is why we do this, right? But yeah, I mean,
that is the explanation that makes the most sense to me is that, and honestly, I don't know when
the practice of having boys serving the altar began but my understanding
is that in most of church history was never boys.
It was a grown man.
Now given, we've raised the age of when someone is a grown man also.
Yeah, sure, sure.
But yeah, but yeah, that was how they would learn the services.
They would learn, oh, this is when we sense this is what the priest does, right?
because the average prissure couldn't see what was going on back there.
Yeah, especially that in detail, right?
Yeah, yeah
Okay, all right. Thanks for calling father nice to talk to you. Okay, okay
I think we're gonna talk about keen
We're gonna make us keep us keen figuring to this
Besides being apparently your favorite kind of chicken delicious chicken
I'm doing all the free commercials tonight.
I know.
Yeah, so yeah, before I got the calls, I was start to say,
we talked in the first half about this distinction between moral and cleanness and ceremonial and cleanness.
And the fact that moral and cleanness includes ceremonial and cleanness.
Right?
And so people may have in their heads, okay, you've got peanut butter and
chives.
you get your peanut butter in my chocolate. Now we've got Reese's, right? But the
the ceremonial uncleanness
that is attached to moral uncleanness
we're making if
what sounds at first like a fine distinction here, but I think you'll see it as we go through this
The kind of ceremonial uncleanness that is attached to moral uncleanness is subtly different as one might
respect. Yeah, they had the same
constructs of being cut off from eating
the sacrifice from a progror, but
they're not the same thing. But it is
a different kind of ceremonial
uncleanness in nature and in
duration. And that's what we're going
to talk about now here in the second
half. Right. And so sort of the
archetypal morally unclean person,
the archetypal sinner from the
the old testicles.
that as far as second-templed Judaism is concerned,
and we see this reflected in the New Testament, is Kane.
Right.
Kane, and of course I mean Kane who killed his brother A
will not quite Chang Kane who walked the earth
to the old man.
Thank you, Grasshopper.
But Kane is this archetypal figure,
and as you mentioned before on the show,
the word sin.
occurs first in the story of Cain in Genesis chapter 4.
So what Adam does is a transgression of God's commandment, right?
And through that, sin comes into the world in Genesis 3.
But sin itself is first mentioned and first does something.
It sort of first appears as such in the story.
when God says to came, sin is crouching at your door, right? It wants to master you, you must master it.
We've talked before on the show, but hey every episode is someone's first.
The verb that's translated crouching there, it is translated bizarrely in the Greek, is actually an
Akkadian word. That's why when they went to translated in the Greek, they didn't know what it meant,
because it's not actually a Hebrew word, it's an Akkadian word.
And Acadian was long gone by that by the 3rd century BC in terms of Alexandria and Jewish
rabbis and their linguistic knowledge.
But that's for that, the King James is where we get the crouching.
That word is a word that in Acadian that was used to describe these demons that they
believed would crawl out of cracks in the earth and sort of roam the land.
And so that's the depiction of sin there as this force.
But Cain is not just sort of, oh he's really bad.
He's a really bad guy.
He's a really bad guy and there are consequences.
There are consequences of the moral uncleanness that he wallows in as a bad guy.
Um.
So, a good place to go for this.
And when I say this, I'm saying, this is not right.
Obviously, Genesis 4 doesn't lay this out verbatim.
But we're talking about it.
We're going to be talking about here,
the understandings for the second temple period,
how they're reading the Cain story.
Yeah.
And then these understandings are reflected in the New Testament.
How they read and understand Cain,
how they read and understand Cape.
particularly as the morally unclean person.
Yeah, yeah.
And so one good example of that is the Book of Wisdom
in chapter 10.
Now, okay, look, I'm calling it the Book of Wisdom
and here's why I'm calling it the Book of Wisdom.
Because I know there's somebody out there, again.
Called the Wisdom of Solomon
and Solomon wrote it and you're a lib
if you don't think that Solomon wrote it.
Okay.
How did you just do comic book guy voice?
Okay, comic book store guy voice.
So okay, look, we need to talk here.
Okay, lots of things in the Bible are referred to as Solomon.
Like the Book of Proverbs.
Guess what? Solomon did write the whole Book of Proverbs.
You know who says that?
The Book of Proverbs.
The Book of Proverbs, yes, it's in there.
That you know, this is a problem of so much of it written by other people.
Okay, but it just gets referred to as one of the works of Solomon.
Okay.
Wisdom traditions are connected.
to disallowing. The Book of Wisdom was written in Greek. The first century BC are possibly even the
first century AD. Yeah, the oldest comments on that book considered to be part of the New Testament.
Yes. That's what I was about to say. The earliest church fathers who referred to the Book of Wisdom
at all, referred to it as part of the New Testament. Okay, so they knew when it was written and that it
was written in great.
They didn't think Solomon literally wrote it.
Okay?
So if you want to be more Orthodox than the church fathers,
if you think you know better than them,
because you've got a Western Bible that calls it
the wisdom of Solomon, and therefore Solomon wrote it
or you're a Lib.
Have fun with yourself.
Yeah, I mean, there's nothing wrong with calling it
the wisdom of Solomon like because wisdom traditions
are connected with Solomon.
And yeah.
Yes, first and second Samuel. Now I know you call those first and second kingdoms because you're being super orthodox, but first and
Samuel guess what? Not written by Samuel. Samuel dies in first Samuel 23.
Just because somebody's name is on a book of the Bible. Does it mean they actually wrote every word of it?
Right. And no one has ever thought so.
Okay, back to King wisdom chapter 10. Yes.
This is the part that I read the book of wisdom but this part I did not remember this.
It says, when an unrighteous man departed from her, and the her there is wisdom, because
it's talking about wisdom.
When an unrighteous man departed from her in his anger, he perished because in rage he
killed his brother.
So this is a reference to Cain.
When the earth was flooded because of him, wisdom again saved it, steering the righteous man
by a paltry piece of wood.
So the flood is blamed here on keen.
Yes, it's his fault.
His fault has to be purified from his evil.
Right, right.
I mean, we'll talk a little bit more about,
wait, how do you connect those dots,
like where is Kane?
It went translation wise.
I know your translation there had
when N-Unrighteous man,
but it's actually what it literally says there is
when V-Unrighteous.
Oh nice.
Like V-Unrighteous one.
Yeah, yeah.
So that's what Kane is being called.
Right?
Yes, the flood was to get rid of the evil
that he spread everywhere.
Wisdom chapter 10 in general the reason there's that departed from her wisdom wisdom chapter 10 is very similar in a lot of ways to
Hebrews chapter 11 the way he was chapter 11 goes through with faithfulness
Like goes through the history biblical history from the perspective of faithfulness wisdom 10 goes through it from the perspective of wisdom
Oh cool. That's why in verses three and four we're talking about Kate
Yeah, yeah, and so referring to is
The unrighteous one seems to have been a common thing in the second
double period. Josephus and his antiquities book one refers to him
the same way. You could read section 53 through 66 for all his
came stuff. Yeah. But calls it the most evil. Right. I mean, one of
the things that's cool to me is like, so there is this this
tradition, which is not explicit in scripture itself, but this
tradition of Noah as the preacher of righteousness. So like is
explicit. Oh, it is.
Oh, excuse me. Where is that?
Say Peter would like a word with you.
There you go. Okay.
It's not explicitly Old Testament.
Yeah. So, so know up, you know, the idea that Noah is preaching to those around him before
the flood comes. And they all hate him. Yeah. Yeah.
Warning him. Morning them. It's not just, oh, look at that.
Weird dude. Weird dude building a gigantic boat in his front yard.
Yeah. He's basically saying repent because the end is near.
And I can't even I can't even
referred to the Bill Cosby routine anymore.
Because I know like the unrighteous.
But, but so Josephus contrasts Noah as the preacher of righteousness with
Kane as the preacher of evil, like this idea that Kane is still around at this point,
like like he's like evil grandpa.
Yes, deliberately encouraging them to do evil.
Yeah, his children and grandchildren and whoever else teaching evil.
and something like this is...
when you have that picture, then you're like, oh, so that's why wisdom describes him as being the one responsible for the flood.
Like he's going around as like the apostle of evil.
Yes, you know, yeah.
Go around telling everybody to be gay and do crimes.
He's the first to him.
Who have I not alienated so far?
Let me know and I'll try to catch them. It's a point before we're done.
Um.
Yeah, and so, yes, we have these sort of dueling, I believe you referred to it earlier as an epic rap battle.
Yes, I can epic rap battle, but we didn't know.
Right, and of course, in the genealogy of Cain, right, that is in Scripture, right, we see how that sort of culminates in Lamek, who's, you know,
uh... polyamorous and uh...
yeah
thanks for paying
for small slides. Right? And particularly sort of like Philo and Josephus, both of them,
with this idea of sort of the continuing corruption and evil growing in the world,
and as a result of Cain sort of producing more of it, point to Tuble Cain inventing metallurgy,
Well, this is basically he has refined murder.
Yeah, right.
Like as if Kane was like, well, yeah, I had to hit him with a rock like what happened at times, right?
Like there's got to be a more efficient way. Yeah, like let's work on some murder tech here you guys for us to kill each other for you to kill man and take their stuff.
So, right, we're what are we going to do, right? Metal energy weapons, right?
And you really see this beginning in Scripture itself with the way Cain is curved.
in Genesis chapter 4. If you compare that to the curse that is an unseated to Adam,
right? So Adam, we've talked about this on the show before but Adam has told
cursed is the ground because of you. Right? So there's sort of there is this evil in
the world. The world itself, the rest of the creation is corrupted by your sin.
Right.
Whereas Canis told
you are cursed from the ground.
Adam's curse means he's going to have to use the sweat of his brow, blood-sweaten tears to bring forth food out of the soil.
Kane has told his curse we'd see he won't be able to get food out of the soil.
Like wild animals will attack him, he will not be able to grow crops.
Right? He is completely alienated from the created order.
by the stain of what he has done.
by the moral uncleanness that he has contracted.
And so if you compare them, the curse that's
adunciated to Cain is a lot more like what God says to the serpent
in Genesis chapter 3, that it is like what he says to his father, Adam.
Right. So this is a different kind of moral uncleanness we're talking about here.
And as we said in the first half, this is associated with murder.
This is one of the big ones.
with blood. And so the word that's used in Greek by these second-tepal era authors that
does not actually occur in the New Testament itself is Agos, Alpha, Yamma, Omicron, Sigma.
or A-G-O-S.
It sounds so barbaric when you
Yeah, which I mean yes, so what does what does August mean then technically speaking means a person
Okay, it is the opposite of pure
Yeah, and I look this up like apparently
Some etymologists think that there is a link with aios
which means holy.
not all agree, but apparently that is a reading that some give of the origin of this word.
And so like if something's accursed, the opposite of pure, it's sort of permanently kicked
out, you know, let him be accursed, you know, anathema, right?
He like, it's just out, whereas Aayos means holy, it means set apart for, you know,
a particular purpose.
And so it's like,
both things that are so both agos and ayos, which even if they're not
etymologically related, makes for a great pun in Greek, they are sort of like
mirror opposites of each other. One is the the good way of being set apart.
The other is the dark, the dark version of being set apart.
From that, really.
Yeah. And this represents a kind of unclean status from moral crimes that in the
extreme cases like can can be permanent.
Why does that reflect itself in terms of nature with king?
Well, we're just coming off of Genesis 1 and 2.
The creation is created as a temple by God.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
Right.
So this expresses itself in him being alienated from the created order.
And these kinds of moral uncleanness that could resulted this permanently ceremonial unclean status.
unclean status.
are sort of these major acts like killing your brother,
killing a family member, gross sacrilege, right?
So Josephus gives an example of a group of priests
who murdered another group of priests in the temple.
Yeah, that's right, at one point.
So they shed blood in the temple, right?
And so that meant that they were permit,
they could never be priesting it.
never serve again, until they're dying day. And Phylo talks about how any active murder or
bloodshed makes someone permanently unable to perform sacred functions. A lot of this is
drawing on the example of King David, right, who was not when he was not allowed to build
the temple.
God, who's now a lot of servant, he was a lot of build it because of the bloodshed.
And these are instances where I mean, we have no evidence whatsoever.
We have no traditions whatsoever that can never repent it.
But David certainly did and services an example of repentance.
But as in David's case, the moral violation, the sin, can be forgiven.
It's not that God can't forgive the sin.
of that.
ritual impurity remains, right? That ritual impurity remains and is permanent in terms of
barring them from certain sacred functions and certain coming to certain closeness with
that is a permanent sort of state that could be contracted.
So...
the moral uncleaness, the sin involved in moral uncleaness and the level and the depth of that sin
sort of changes the nature of the attached ceremonial uncleaness.
So the kind of ceremonial uncleaness attached to moral uncleaness is not we're not just talking about
regular ceremonial uncleaness which is the common, right?
it's just common there's there's no vibrations of
This is a sort of consequence of sin,
is being barred from that is a consequence of sin.
It's hard to use English words
because like sacred and profane
originally just meant holy and common, right?
Yeah, I mean, profane literally means outside the temple.
Right.
And so we have to profane in the sense
that we talk about pro.
vanity maybe, right? Like that this is something that's incompatible. You have contracted a state that is a permanent state that
cannot then come into
into the presence of God at least in this life because in a normal case, right? Our normal case is
You go you sin
you repent and do everything involved with repentance.
And then you come in a...
and offer sacrifice in your restored.
The sacrifice is really the celebration of the restoration.
It's not the repentance itself.
If you don't have the repentance
then the sacrifice is meaningless.
Scripture is pretty clear.
In fact God will reject that sacrifice
if there's not repentance attached to it.
But offering that sacrifice requires ceremonial cleanness.
Right? So in most cases, once you've completed the process of repentance, then you can wash,
and you can become ceremonially clean again, even though you contracted that ceremonial
uncleanness through sin. But in these extreme cases, right, because that ritual or ceremonial
impurity is permanent in this life. Right?
You can't go and offer the sacrifice that would end that period.
You remain.
So in the way this was understood in the Second Temple Jewish world, like by Josephus and
Philover, we're talking about this and other authors.
We're talking about this is that the person's death, the person dying is what brings about
what we would call absolution.
What we...
Christian church circles would call absolution, right? So sort of that moral
uncleaness, the end of it, what removes it is the person's physical death.
Keep that idea in mind when you read St. Paul saying, talk about handing
someone over to Satan for the destruction of their body and the salvation of
their soul. Yeah, right. That idea. And
And this is reflected in our own canons where there are certain sins that are considered
so severe that you're functionally excommunicated until you're deathbed.
Right.
I mean, people might be surprised to learn that that's in a bunch of the canons.
Yeah.
I mean, it's now that's not the canons are not self-applying.
Right.
You know, they have to be applied by the bishop, really.
But that is what the canons say in many cases.
There are certain ones that says they're excommunicated until they're about to die.
You can hear them.
imagine horrific things someone could do, right?
Where anyone would think that was appropriate, right?
That's not, this isn't prescribed by the canons
were the kind of things that people normally do.
Right, this is very extreme cases, right?
And you have to remember, for a lot of the church's history,
Everyone was born into the church.
and baptized into the church. Right, so people who today we would call sociopaths
or psychopath people who would do these horrific things were probably baptized
into the Orthodox church when they were infants. If they were happened to have been
born in the Eastern Roman Empire. Right, so there were people who were quote-unquote
questions who would go and do these horrific things.
Right, now obviously they didn't do them as Christians, but they're technically within
the church.
And so the church would have to have ways of dealing with that.
And so you do this very, every thing.
We don't have this that much of the US because the kind of people who do these horrific things
usually aren't very religious.
Right.
Yeah.
You know, Jeffrey Dahmer, not, you know, super pious, right?
Guy.
Charles Manson was, I guess, religious in a weird way.
certainly was in Orthodox.
Right? And so even if one of those figures converted to orthodox Christianity, we'd be dealing with a different sort of situation.
Right? Those cannons are talking about someone who is an orthodox Christian, goes and does these horrific things.
And says, well, you know what? They need to remain part of the church, but their repentance, the period of their repentance before their restored is going to be the rest of their natural life.
Hmm, that's going to be the period of their repentance.
And...
what we see there and what the idea is behind this in the earlier Jewish view too, is that
the state of being ceremonially unclean, right? Even if it's permanent, for a long period of time
or permanently, is itself part of the repentance? Yeah. Accepting that is part of the repentance.
Remaining at a little bit of a remove is part of...
of the repents. And David, we see this very clearly in the case of David. Right? David gets
cold. He can't build the temple. He accepts it. Lays out all the plans, puts aside all
the building materials, says, my son will do it. Right? But I'm not going to do it. And
everything that happens at his family, everything that happens, he says, this is because of my
and I accept he accepts all of the consequences.
Right, and what he's done.
One of our problems in the modern world is that people frankly, because they don't understand repentance,
they think they have a right to be forgiven and they think being forgiven means everyone just forgets about what they did.
Yeah, everything goes back to where it was before.
Yeah.
And some things that you can't fix in this life.
Yeah, and that's not right.
Somebody embezzles money from the church.
Okay, they can't ever be the church treasure again.
Right, like you don't have to make them the church trash.
in order to forgive them. So when harms a child, they're not allowed to be a Sunday school teacher, right?
There should be obvious, right? And the fact that you don't make them one doesn't mean you're not, you haven't, they, you're not forgiven.
That's not what that means at all, right? Part of their repentance is accepting
the fact that there are going to be certain things they can never do now because of what they've done in the past.
No, right, accepting that and working to serve God with it.
in those strictures that they brought upon themselves,
that's part of what it means to repent.
So the way that ceremonial uncleanness
is typically dealt with, as we mentioned,
in the Torah and the Old Testament as a whole,
is through ritual washing, right?
But that's not how you deal with moral uncleanness.
Right, for our reasons.
You're all you damn-
you touch a dead body, you touch some mildew.
Okay, you go and you wash, right?
But you kill somebody,
you can't just go wash your hands, take a shower,
take a good shower, get all the blood off of you.
Okay, now we're good, right?
Obviously, right.
And that's a discontinuity,
an area of discontinuity between the ritual washings
in the mix.
vote in the scriptures and baptism. Because baptism, even beginning with St. John,
for the forgiveness of sins, for the remission of sins, is talking about
washing away moral and moral ceremonial uncleanness. Right? That's what's
getting washed away by baptism.
That's part of why...
It's only done once as opposed to those other ritual wash-ups.
Yeah, and in that much, it's not dealing with those day-to-day things.
Right. It's a much greater thing too.
Like it has the ability to wash away moral uncleanness.
Yes.
A murderer can be baptized and become a new person.
Right.
Yeah.
Yes.
And this is why certain sins, canonical impediments to different things like
of ordination.
are dealt with differently if they happen before baptism
rather than after baptism.
And I know some people look at those cases
in the Orthodox Church and say,
oh, you're saying if it wasn't in the Orthodox Church,
it doesn't count.
We're not saying anything like that.
We're saying something about baptism and what baptism does.
Right?
Yep, yep.
All of that quote unquote counts.
But baptism represents a real putting off
man and putting out of the new man. It represents a real beginning of a new creation.
Right? And there is nothing else after baptism that does that. See the book of Hebrews, right?
There's nothing after baptism. Once you are a follower of Christ, right? Where once you're
already a follower of Christ, you go and commit these actions. Now you deal with the period of
repentance, and the means of repentance is prescribed by the Church.
because you are now in a different place, right?
Spiritually, literally, in a different place, right?
You are now in the presence of God.
You are now performing these actions
in the presence of God.
And we'll get into that more in our third half.
Exactly.
All right, thanks everybody.
We'll be right back in just a second.
Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Stephen D. Young
will be back in a moment to take your calls
on the next part of the Lord of Spirits.
Give them a call at 855-237-2346. That's 855-AF radio.
How do you explain the sacraments? It's easy to say they're mysteries that we have to take on
faith or on the authority of tradition, but that is not how the early Christians understood them.
To them, and to all ancient people, the idea that physical objects had spiritual power was very
intuitive.
Whereas modern people tend to find this difficult, bizarre, or even un-Christian.
This is because we live in an era shaped by secularism, a way of viewing a world that's
incompatible with sacramental thinking.
Because secular ideas are at the heart of our culture, modern people tend to think in
secular ways without realizing it, even the most well-meaning of us.
How then do we live in, but not be of, a secular culture?
You need to understand the enchanted, sacramental way that the early Christians viewed the world.
But we also need to understand secularism.
What is it really?
Where did it come from?
And how does it influence how we think about religion?
Journey to Reality, Sacramento Life in a secular age,
breaks down these important issues in accessible,
non-academic language and is an ideal introduction for young readers,
catacuments and seekers,
as well as for any Orthodox Christians who want to deepen their understanding of the sacraments.
Journey to Reality, Sacramento Life in a secular age, by Zachary Porkou.
Now we do
at www.store.enginefaith.com.
Again, that is store.enginefaith.com.
We're back now with the Lord of Spirits,
the Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Stephen DeYoung.
If you have a question, call now at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF radio.
Welcome back everybody.
We're talking about ritual on cleanness
cleanness and sleep.
so forth. And we just we just spent the second half discussing the character of moral ritual
uncleaness and that it's not just simply ritual uncleaness plus a bad thing. It is a different
a different character to it. So all right. Well, let's let's talk about atonement. What do you think,
Father? Yeah. So what is that could have completely rehearse everything from our day of atonement
episode. Yes, which I will...
say by the way it's still one of my favorite episodes. I mean that's a few years old now but
yeah check out it's called there. It might be true. It's called the priest shall make
a tonement pretty straightforward. Again does what it says on the tin. Yeah yeah yeah yeah.
Yeah go listen to that everybody. So yeah we're not going to rehearse all what three hours of that
or so, you're the third half of this episode, but just to briefly cover a couple things.
we talked about there to lead into some things we're talking about here. We talked about there how the
day of atonement was an additional annual ritual, additional to the regular cycle of sin offerings
and peace offerings, etc. that were going on to the tabernacle all the time. So this is an additional
thing. And so that sort of begs the question, well, okay.
what sins still needed to be a tone for that wasn't being covered by the sin offerings,
because I thought that's what the sin offerings did, right?
Yeah.
And so we talked about how the day of atonement is not concerned primarily with the sin
per se, in the sense that the sin offerings were ultimately the celebration of the end of
the period of repentance and the reconciliation and the reentry into the community, but the
The day of a telecom was concerned with sort of the taint the-
uncleanness left behind by the sins of the people over the course of the year.
And that sort of
tape or spore that was left behind by the people's sins over the course of the year
was especially dangerous within the sanctuary of the tabernacle. It was especially dangerous on
that day because that is the day that Yahweh that got of Israel chose to appear to manifest
himself.
in the Holy of Holies. And of course there could be no sin, no uncleanness in his presence.
And so the Day of Atonement rituals are preparatory rituals to purify the sanctuary for that.
We also in that episode talked about what is basically the topic of my
previous dissertation, which again, I'm not going to recap the hundreds of pages,
hundreds and hundreds of footnotes for you here.
the way all the people who review my books and just love footnotes and miss them.
Grab my dissertation, man, there's more than 700.
All the footnotes you could ever want.
I know.
People are so funny.
Beautiful and lined up in a row.
But that was on 1st John 2 verse 2, right?
That Christ is the atonement for our sins and not only for our sins, but also for the whole
world and how that's talking about the world.
the creation. The material creation is cleansed and purified by Christ's blood and sort of an
eschatological day of atonement. The creator in order is cleansed from the stain, the effects of man's
sin, right? And it's talking about removing this sort of moral ceremony, it'll take the comes from
from human evil, from the material world.
Okay, now that's said, so that's recap, right?
Now someone might misunderstand or deliberately misunderstand.
That to be said so we can take that it's okay universalist way.
Okay well now there's nothing unclean in the world.
No.
There's nothing unclean at all.
That's cleaned everything.
Take it some kind of universalist way.
Right.
Well that should mean anyone should be able to approach God at any time because everything
and everyone is clean now.
So counter to that, we have plenty of
passages in the New Testament that still talk about the distinction between clean things and unclean things.
And a good example of that is in 2 Corinthians 6 verse 17.
Yes, where it says,
therefore,
go out from their midst and be separate from them, says the Lord,
and touch no unclean thing,
then I will welcome you.
Sorry, Calvinists about that then.
Yeah.
But clearly, whenever else we want to say about this verse, we leave the Calvary alone for
now.
Right.
Clearly, St. Paul is applying that there are still unclean things from which we need to separate
ourselves as Christians.
Right.
In fact, if you read that whole passage in 2 Corinthians 6, St. Paul is arguing from the
idea that now we as Christians our bodies are
the temples of the Holy Spirit, and therefore the need for purity in our lives is actually heightened
by the presence of the Holy Spirit. We need to be more concerned about purity and being clean
and being holy than people did previously, who did not have the Holy Spirit dwelling within them.
And this, of course, for St. Paul broadly has to do with the process of repentance and sacrifice
sacrifice here being for us the Eucharist.
Right, where this is applied to us.
Right, and we maintain this holiness.
But so there are things.
Now, when we say that, there are things that are clean,
you may have immediately thought, well, yeah, obviously,
there are things that are morally unclean.
Right, pornography is unclean.
Yeah.
Right, the blood of a murder victim, when you murdered them,
is like, clearly, that's still immorally uncleaned.
Right, these horrible crimes, sexual immorality.
and morality.
Unclean, right? That may be where your mind jumped, but there are also things that are still ceremonially unclean.
Yes, it's like feces. Right. Right.
It cannot, you know, if you have that on you, you cannot enter in. Yes.
Feces is not suddenly clean and holy now. Right?
Then you covered it. Road kill.
Sorry, fellow southerners. It's not suddenly clean and holy.
And then you'll have it corpses decomposing corpse
corpses are not suddenly clean and holy in the New Covenant.
So there's all those obviously morally unclean things, but there are things that are just
unclean in that ceremonial sense.
They require washing, the purification still.
And for us, we still have the churchy that we talked about with the collar in the second
half.
We still practice that.
That was actually that particular practice of the Orthodox church was one of the points
of criticism.
from Rome at the Council of Florence.
There were Roman bishops at the Council of Florence
who accused the Orthodox of being judyizers,
bringing me those things.
Interesting footnote.
Right.
But so the reason those unclean things,
those ceremonially unclean things remain,
is why?
Well, the common remains.
There's still things that are holy and things that are common.
And Christianity is not about making every common thing in the world holy.
We're not trying to make every cup of chalice.
Yeah, some are just here with the Eucharist.
You know, start trek two, wrath of con commemorative cup.
Right.
There is no such thing as a holy toilet.
It doesn't matter how nice you make it.
I'll read you all super
it. It's still a toilet. Yeah, okay. And you're gonna spend your life coming into contact with
things that aren't holy, with things that are common. Even if you're a monastic, monastics aren't like
in the chapel all day every day. No, no. They're all right. Working. Yes, with a common thing,
Right?
Howing root of it is.
I think that's big or the next one is stairs.
Hoeing root of babies.
Hoeing root of babies?
Yes.
That's the biggest activity.
But just common things, right?
There's nothing wrong with that.
That's normal, right?
You will have to eat things in life other than the Eucharist.
Yep.
Even if you receive the Eucharist every day,
you're not gonna live on it.
Miracles of particular saints aside.
Right, like don't bring up the same Mary of Egypt,
you're not saying Mary of Egypt, right?
You're gonna eat some things other than the Eucharist
in a couple of pieces of bread, okay?
And so there is because we live our whole world still
in the new covenant, in the New Testament today,
as Christians.
We still live in the world of the common, right?
The common world, the unclean world, right?
And then we come at certain...
times to approach God, to present ourselves to God. We come to encounter the holy. Most often,
that is at church. Sometimes it is not, right? Sometimes it is with our family gathering for prayer.
Sometimes it is by ourselves, right? But we come to encounter the holy. And when we come to encounter
the whole thing, we prepare ourselves.
Yeah, and I mean, and this is why like
As we mentioned earlier when we were talking to father who called in,
and as he mentioned, there's handwashing for the clergy at particular points,
whether it's at the end of vesting or with a bishop during the liturgy,
or in some traditions, actually all the clergy who are going to
commune will wash their hands.
But also, and actually someone just brought this up on the YouTube chat,
there's this question.
I mean, this is another one of these ground zero things.
It's so funny, people always make it about the stuff that women do.
without talking about that men have a responsibility just as much in this regard.
Like there is still the custom that many women have of during their time of the month,
not receiving Holy Communion. But that's not a special thing to women, because the
the loss of bodily fluids also applies to men. As we said, these things are directly connected in
in the viticus.
know, and it's reflected in the cannons of the church. You know, it is.
And you clean yourself. Right. And you come back. And you yeah. Right. So, you know, and
but I'll say, I mean, I think it's important to note that like, this is not something
that you enforce upon other people. This is something that is within the pastoral relationship.
Yes, you know.
Yeah, it's, I mean, I've heard of, of, of, of, and I think it might be easier to treat women this way because you just know that women if they're of a certain age are having their time of the month every month and so like, oh, look at her she went to communion six weeks in a row.
like, you know, whereas with men with, you know, the parallel issues with men, you don't know, like it's not on a cycle.
But, but nonetheless, this is just one of those things. It's like, hello, you do not.
force that on up on other people. That is something that each person, you know, in their
spiritual discipline and their piety is being worked out with their spiritual father.
But the important thing is our focus is exactly reverse from what it should be.
Yeah. Our focus is always on this separation.
Yeah. Our focus is always on the time of separation.
No, it's the focus of the church. The focus of of of of orthodox Christianity is on the returning.
Yes, exactly, in that...
That's one of the things that when, when, when, you know, sometimes people are offended by the fact that holy communion in the Orthodox church is reserved for Orthodox Christians.
And so they'll say like, well, why won't you commune me or why won't you commune my uncle or whatever. I'll say, look, I want to.
But there's some things we need to do first.
You are welcome to communion.
When you've gone through, when you've done what?
But the members of this community have all done.
You know, that's what it is.
I guess the door is open, but you need to walk the path.
You know, but yeah, the point is to get people to be.
Oh yeah, well, I do tend to be nicer than you.
Yeah, because I would say something like, hey man, if you come visit my house, you can
have any of the food in the fridge, you can drink any of my liquor, but you can't have
thanks with my life.
I mean, that analogy that your angry emails about that analogy to father Andrew David, that
analogy also works, but obviously it has certain limitations.
It's not like, well, if you as long you go through these steps, then you can, no, no, no,
no.
But yeah, like you said, the point is to have that communion with God.
It's not about figuring out ways to prevent people having that communion from God.
It's about going there in the right way.
On the purpose of preparation and purification and entering appropriately.
Because like St. Paul said, some of you were not doing it the right way and so some of
you are sick and some of you are dead.
Yeah.
You know, all the commandments of the Torah, all these things we've been talking about,
right, were to facilitate God being able to dwell among His people and then being able
to approach Him in worship.
Right.
aimed at not be opposite, not keeping them away, not barring them, not excluding them.
It's not fencing the table. Right. And so there are these times that they're built in, right, times of repentance.
We don't we don't consecrate the Eucharist on weekdays during Lent in the Orthodox Church, following the Canon from Nicaea, right.
because we have these times of separation to enable
return, preparation to return, right, and to return in the appropriate way, in the prepared way.
Yep, the purified way.
Yep.
Well, here we are at the end of the third half of this episode of Lurus Spear.
This topic was actually requested by multiple people, including me.
Like we've talked about it a little bit on previous episodes here and there.
But I thought it would be a good idea to do like a focused, you know, especially because we have the feast of
the meeting of the Lord in the temple as it's called in Orthodox practice in Western practice. It's called
the purification of the Virgin
Interestingly enough or Candle Miss is kind of the shorthand colloquial term because there's a tradition of blessing candles for this upcoming feast and
I
I love, I love Candlemas. I love this feast where Christ is brought as a 40-day old
child to the temple and taken into the arms of Simeon the righteous. You see exactly,
exactly the practice, I mean it's from the Torah but we see this happening with Jesus with
his mother, the Thayer Tokos, and this is exactly our practice in the Orthodox Church.
is that a mother and her new child
come to the door of the church.
And she is, there are rituals of purification done for her.
In Orthodox practice, it is that the priest says,
prayers over her, lays his hand on her head,
prays that she would be cleansed,
prays that her sins would be forgiven,
not the sin of having a baby because that's not a sin.
But the sins that she just committed
during your time.
of being away from church for six weeks, so they're speaking we return to holy communion.
And then also prayers for the offering of that child to God.
Because that's the point, like we were just saying, that's the point.
And so there's so much that we do in the church that's all aimed at this.
like it's for our purification so that we can have this communion with God.
God. I mean, and this is fructally applicable too, right? So that's the highest, greatest,
the most central instantiation of that is that we purify ourselves so that we can approach
God and communion with Him. But like, this is also true in our relationships, right? You
You can't have communion with your spouse, with your family, with your friends.
there's
uncleanness between you. If there's unforgiven, unrepented sins between you, you can't. It's
impaired. I think this is probably the most obvious in terms of husbands and wives, that
the intimacy of husbands and wives, the union of husbands and wives, and I don't just mean
the physical unit.
and although it definitely expresses itself there,
it's predicated upon a cleanness between them.
A cleanness between them.
This life is given to us for repentance.
And repentance is not just like, you know, I'm sorry,
I'm not going to do it again.
I'm going to try to do good things from now on.
Of course, that's all required.
But
repentance is aimed at intimacy with God.
That's what it's aimed at. It's not just so you become a better person.
Right? Like what's offered to us is to be sons of the most high, to be equal to angels, to be part of the royal family of God himself,
to be adopted into his family. That is what has offered to us. And so all of
repentance, all of this purification, all of this is aimed at getting us ready for that.
Getting us ready for that.
So far from the idea of richable uncleanness and purification being left behind in the
old covenant, having nothing to do with the new covenant, I would say that really, in
many, in, at least from this angle, it is what everything that we're doing as Christians
of the new covenant.
is we're being clenched, we're being clenched so that we can have this intimacy, this communion with God.
It's a beautiful thing.
Father?
So there are a couple of wrong terms I think that we make in contemporary culture.
regarding the idea of the holy and the common.
or the sacred and the profane, if understood correctly, the holy and the common.
One of those comes to us a lot from mostly from certain areas within American even
angelicalism, which is not the same thing as Protestantism.
And that comes in the form of, I mean, it could sound an awful lot like the aforementioned
with the color Korra, you know, are not all in Israel holding, where it's just sort
of, oh, everyone's a saint, right?
Everything's holy.
Every place is holy.
God is everywhere, right?
And going down that road, what you really end up with is not everyone is holy, but no
What is holy?
Not every place is holy, but no place is really holy.
You get a kind of license to do what you want,
dress how you want, right, and call it church and do whatever,
but there's no holy place, there's no holy time,
there's no holy people, that's where you end up.
And you lose any concept of reverence that,
reverence for particular people,
reverence for particular places, particular times,
regular times.
You lose any sense of preparation, preparing to be God or anything.
And church just becomes one more common activity, right?
That's part of just the common life.
In fact, more and more it just starts to look like all the other aspects of your life.
There's less and less difference because, again, everything is just common.
other and sometimes this happens as a reaction.
Sometimes this happens as a reaction.
action from somebody who was in that world and now is in a tradition that has more
of a sense of the holy. They become Roman Catholic, they become some kind of high church Protestant,
they become Orthodox. But this also, you find this same error actually in a different form in
puretism and pietism. And that is the idea that there is the holy and there is the common
And the holy is good and the common is somehow bad and then it is the holy.
Right.
And this expresses itself, again in these various forms.
For an Orthodox convert, this may take the form of them,
kind of desperately wanting to be a monastic, even though they're not a monastic.
and even monastics are not actually as we mentioned in the Church 20
24-7, they're doing other things.
But this person, you know, the only music they will listen to
is chant CDs from the church.
The only thing they will read is things about the Orthodox Church,
although a lot of those things seem to be on social media
for some reason, rather than the books,
the writings of the fathers themselves.
Right, and they just want to be totally immersed,
sort of like in the church, a hundred percent of the time.
Right, and that leads to bad places.
They a lot of them end up flaring out and leaving the church.
They burn out. Other things happen. They cause a lot of trouble in the meantime.
Some good cases, they kind of get more balanced as they go. That's what we hope for.
But the same thing happens to Roman Catholic Church.
The high church Protestant groups, the people who do this.
In the more purest and pious form, this is...
you know, in the pious part of the duchre form tradition, I was exposed to this,
where certain people, you know, while we are not legalists, right, and would never say,
you know, xyz, those Baptists are crazy for saying you can't do xyz. Do you really need to go
out to eat on a Sunday. It's a different list of rules for everybody, but...
Right? That, and the whole, there's also even in the Piotis Dutch tradition, there was a whole
worldly amusement thing. Right? Like, why are you dancing? Why are you playing cards? Right?
And of course people can see that spread out through the pure tradition.
Sort of amusing yourself. Anything that's just common like that.
Anything that isn't somehow spiritually directed.
right is somehow bad.
And so whatever you're gonna do,
if your kids gonna read a children's book,
well you've gotta go and get a Christian children's book
from the bookstore.
And if they're gonna listen to music,
you gotta see, I don't know, nobody uses CDs anymore,
but you get my point.
You're gonna listen to music,
well it's gotta be the Christian version of that music.
If you're gonna listen to rock music,
it's gotta be Christian rock music.
If you're gonna listen to rap music,
it's gotta be Christian rap music.
Whatever it is, we have to Christianize it,
because we have to make everything.
We have to try to make everything holy.
We can't ever be out there in the common world, right?
That's the low church Protestant form of it,
that pure form of it.
And all of that is a mistake.
All that is a mistake and nothing the scriptures
they were called for.
Nothing the church ever called for.
The church, the scriptures have always been out
as people we live out in the common world.
And then at certain times, we gather together as families, as a whole church community,
we gather together to worship God, to enter the presence of God, to draw close to God.
And before we do that, we sort of mentally and physically and spiritually prepare ourselves
to sort of leave that common world and come into the presence of God.
We do that for a time.
And then after we've done that for a time, we don't build tabernacles there, we go back
down the mountain, and we go back into the common world of everyday life.
And we embrace everyday life as also being good.
The common is also good.
It's okay to watch a movie with your family.
Okay
the sports ball on Sunday afternoon after you get home from
literature, which you didn't skip to watch the sports ball.
It's okay to play a video game once a while.
It's okay to just read a novel that has no spiritual
importance whatsoever.
It's okay for your kids to imagine and play games and things
that aren't directly related to Christianity or the
that you're somehow.
It's okay to live a normal life in the world, as long as, when the time comes, we set
that aside.
We prepare ourselves, we purify ourselves, and we come again into the presence of God.
There's going to come a day where the presence of God is going to completely fill the entire
universe, and we're going to dwell with Him forever.
That day will come, but that day is not today.
Today we have to pay.
Today we have to feed ourselves.
Today we have to maintain our car.
Today we have a thousand other these common things to do.
And doing them isn't bad.
It isn't wrong.
It isn't a distraction from good things.
Right?
And I'll finish up with this.
A place where we see this is the
everyone talks about the story of St. Mary and Martha.
Because the way you may have heard it in the past is,
we'll say Martha, she's going around busy doing all this work preparing hospitality to receive
guests, right? And St. Mary, she's sitting there listening to Jesus and St. Mary is the good example
and St. Martha is the bad example. You should be like St. Mary, not like St. Martha.
I'm kind of obviated by the fact that they're both saints.
This is because people don't read closely.
Because what Christ says to St. Martha is that there is one thing
needful for her.
And that is what St. Mary is doing.
He doesn't say there's anything wrong with her serving.
Hospitality is good.
Hospitality is the right thing to do.
Everything in the St. Martha was...
doing was good, but there was one additional thing she needed. And that was at a certain
point. Having done all of the business of the world, all the meal preparation, all the
everything, all the hospitality preparation, the time would come when she needed that one
thing, which was to come into the presence of the Lord and come and sit at Jesus' feet
and listen to him. These things are not opposed to each other. They go together. It's
with a dome.
go together that there's a problem.
Well, thank you very much everyone. That's our show for tonight. We appreciate you
listening. If you didn't happen to get through to us live, we'd still like to hear
from you. You can email us at LordOfSpiritsofHinFate.com. You can message us at
our Facebook page. You can also leave us a voice mail at SpeakPipe.com slash Lord
Of Spirits. And if you have basic questions about Orthodox Christianity or
or you need help to find a parish.
go to orthodoxintro.org.
Joyce will rely broadcasts on the second and fourth Thursdays of the month at 7pm Eastern,
4pm Pacific.
Teddy Pettergrass is cooler than Freddie Jackson's sip of milkshake in a snowstorm.
If you're on Facebook you can follow our page, you can join our discussion group and you
can please leave ratings and reviews on all the appropriate places and share this show
with one of your friends.
I'd probably be sure to go to htfaith.com, stroke support and help make sure we, lots of
whether AFR podcasters.
on the air. We're going to ride out to the honeycomb hideout. I'm going to show you how to
wild out like Jack Tripple. Thank you, good night, and may God bless you always.
You've been listening to the Lord of Spirits with Orthodox Christian priests, Father Andrew
Stephen Damick and Father Stephen DeYoung, a listener supported presentation of
faith radio. And I be held and I heard the voice of many angels round about the throne
and the beasts and the elders and the number of them was 10,000 times 10,000 than
thousands of thousands, saying with a loud voice worthy as the land that was slain to receive power
and riches and wisdom and strength and honor and glory and blessing. Revelation chapter 5.